Finding Aid for Robert E. Lewis papers, 1972-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Robert E. Lewis papers 1972-2012 1972-1985
Lewis, Robert E.
2011099 Aa 2
Robert E. Lewis served as editor-in-chief of the Middle English Dictionary at the University of Michigan from 1982 to 2001. Before coming to Michigan Lewis was a professor of English at Indiana University where he co-authored A Guide to the Manuscripts of the Prick of Conscience. The Robert E. Lewis papers relate primarily to research into Prick of Conscience, the most popular English poem of the Middle Ages. The papers include correspondence, articles, notes and reproductions (photocopies and microfilm) of medieval manuscripts and texts of the poem and related material
4.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were received from Robert E. Lewis (donor no. 9126 ) in 2011 and 2013.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Robert E. Lewis received his B.A. degree from Princeton University in 1959 and his M.A. and Ph.D. degrees from The University of Pennsylvania in 1962 and 1964, respectively. He was appointed to the faculty of Indiana University in 1963 and rose to the rank of professor in 1975. Lewis joined the University of Michigan faculty in 1982 as professor and co-editor of the Middle English Dictionary (MED) and research scientist and was promoted to editor in 1983. He was named executive director of the MED in 1990. Begun in 1930, the MED survived the Depression and World War II and is the most important research project in the humanities to date at the University of Michigan. In 2001, the printed dictionary arrived at the end of the alphabet, and almost simultaneously the electronic version came on line completely searchable and available for supplementation and correction. With nearly 15,000 printed pages, the MED is a centerpiece for research in medieval English culture. Lewis also contributed to medieval studies, particularly in his essays on Chaucer and the Prick of Conscience. A skilled bibliographer, Lewis was co-editor of the Index of Printed Middle English Prose (1985). Upon his retirement in 2003, Lewis was named professor emeritus of English language and literature, executive director emeritus of the Middle English Dictionary, and research scientist emeritus.
Source: Proceedings of the Board of Regents of the University of Michigan, December 2003.
-------------------------------
Source: Proceedings of the Board of Regents of the University of Michigan, December 2003.
History of Prick of Conscience Studies
The Prick of Conscience, to judge from the number of known manuscripts (120), was the most popular English poem of the Middle Ages, surpassing such popular poems as Geoffrey Chaucer's Canterbury Tales (its nearest competitor with 64 manuscripts), Piers Plowman (with 54), and John Gower's Confessio Amantis (with 51), and was itself surpassed in English only by the two versions of the Wycliffite prose translation of the Bible and the prose Brut. The poem exists in three versions: (1) an original or main version (in 99 manuscripts), which originated in the north of England, probably Yorkshire, with a preponderance of manuscripts from that area and the north midlands, but also extending into the west midlands and East Anglia and even into the southeast and the southwest; (2) a shorter, thoroughly revised recension (in nineteen manuscripts) originating somewhere in the south, with a more restricted distribution; and (3) a heavily revised and abbreviated version of the main version entitled Speculum Huius Vite (in two manuscripts).
The popularity of the poem is supported by other signs: eighty per cent of the counties of England can claim at least one copy of the poem, some have two or more, and three of the copies are written in the Anglo-Irish dialect; extracts circulated separately (twelve in eight manuscripts); the poem was quoted in a number of other Middle English poems ("Stimulus Consciencie Minor," "Desert of Religion," "Of the Flood of the World," "Wheel of Fortune," for example) as well as in a stained glass window at All Saints Church in York); there was a translation into Latin prose made in the 14th century (six manuscripts exist); and the poem appears in wills and book lists.
The Prick of Conscience is a long verse compilation (over 9,600 lines in rhyming couplets), divided into a prologue; seven books, which treat, in turn, the wretchedness of man's nature throughout his life, the world and the various conditions thereof, death and the fear of death, purgatory and its characteristics, the day of judgment, the pains of hell, and the joys of heaven; and a brief conclusion or epilogue. The poem has a great many sources: ultimately over twenty separate works, primarily Latin, including both well known ones like St. Augustine's De Civitate Dei, Honorius of Autun's Elucidarium, Pope Innocent III"s De Miseria Humane Conditionis, and Bartholomeus Anglicus's De Proprietatibus Rerum and not so well known ones like Robert Grosseteste's De Penis Purgatorii (in its French version) and Hugh Ripelin of Strasbourg's Compendium Theologice Veritatis.
For a long time the poem was thought to have been written by the well known hermit and mystical writer Richard Rolle (died 1349), to whom it is attributed in five manuscripts, but his authorship is now considered extremely doubtful. Three manuscripts attribute the poem to Robert Grosseteste (circa 1170-1253), Bishop of Lincoln, but he lived too early to be the author. A more recent suggestion is William of Nassyngton (died 1359), chancellor of the Diocese of York and the author of the Speculum Vite, but there is as yet no proof for this. In genre the Prick of Conscience is unlike any other Middle English work in verse or prose, though it has some similarities and has been compared to the Speculum Vite. Its primary function was probably as a compendium of knowledge from which a parish priest could instruct his flock or draw material for his sermons, and its wide circulation in the 14th and 15th centuries indicates that it must have fulfilled its purpose.
The poem is worth studying for a number of reasons and from a variety of points of view, and when Lewis came to Ann Arbor in 1982 he had just completed, with Angus McIntosh A Guide to the Manuscripts of the Prick of Conscience (Oxford: Society for the Study of Medieval Languages and Literature), which they hoped, as they said in their Preface, would "stimulate and facilitate research into some of the important... questions connected with [the poem], such as its genre, the reasons for its popularity, its audience, and its influence in Britain in the later Middle Ages"; and Lewis himself was planning to spend whatever free time he had on various aspects of the poem. He had made good progress on two projects: the sources (and the manuscript tradition of the sources) of Book I and an edition of one of the short poems indebted to the Prick of Conscience, the "Stimulus Consciencie Minor." But the work of the Middle English Dictionary took precedence during his official working years, and because of other commitments he was unable to complete these projects during retirement. He deposited his Prick of Conscience materials in the Bentley Library in the hope that other researchers would consult them as a starting point either to complete the two projects he began or to study other aspects of the poem.
Scope and Content Note
The Robert E. Lewis papers relate primarily to research and study of the Prick of Conscience the most popular English poem of the Middle Ages. Prick of Conscience material includes reproductions (photocopies and microfilm) of medieval manuscripts and related Middle English texts as well as Lewis's correspondence, notes, and research files on the Prick of Conscience. Material relating to the Middle English Dictionary and his professional career is also present.
The Lewis papers are arranged in five series. The first four series relate to the poem Prick of Conscience: Prick of Conscience, Related Materials, Notes on Cards and Slips, and Microfilms of Manuscripts. The content of the first two boxes are all in standard archival folders and are arranged by subject. In box three the materials represent a variety of formats (4" x 6" cards, 5" x 8" cards and slips, and a paperback book), also arranged by subject, with a few microfilms in various kinds of containers. The final box consists of microfilms only.
Subjects:
Lewis, Robert E.; English language--Middle English, 1100-1500.; Manuscripts, Medieval--England.; Prick of conscience.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
- Prick of Conscience
  The series Prick of Conscience contains correspondence 1972-1982, arranged from earliest to latest between Lewis and Angus McIntosh, of the University of Edinburgh, primarily about the preparation of their book, A Descriptive Guide to the Manuscripts of the Prick of Conscience (1982) as well as correspondence with Derek Britton (also of the University of Edinburgh), another researcher on various aspects of the Prick of Conscience, between 1974 and 1980, and occasional other scholars and librarians. Also included are reviews of Lewis and McIntosh's Descriptive Guide.
  The remainder of the series is devoted to various aspects of the poem: its manuscripts (both on groups of manuscripts and on individual manuscripts, chiefly of the main version); its other versions (the interpolated variants of the main version, the southern recension, and the revised and abbreviated Speculum Huius Vite); its sources (both in general and specifically for each of four books out of seven, with an emphasis on Book I, which Lewis had spent most of his time on); the authorship of the poem; its popularity and audience; and its influence (both in general and specifically in the short poem "Stimulus Consciencie Minor"), with an additional file on the manuscripts of the latter poem in preparation for an edition, on which Lewis was working.
  In all of the files on aspects of the poem, the organization adheres to the following pattern: general statement(s), if any, on the subject in question; specific correspondence, if any, about the subject, in chronological order; printed articles, if any, on the subject; and notes (chiefly handwritten) on the subject, in no particular order.
  The remainder of the series contains photocopies of manuscripts of the Prick of Conscience, in alphabetical order by the city and library in which they are housed, and they are followed by Lewis's collation sheets for selected lines of the main version, which he used to determine relationships among and between manuscripts.
  - Notes on Individual Manuscripts (Box 1)
    - General (Box 1)
    - Arundel Castle Manuscript (Box 1)
    - Vernon and Simeon Manuscripts (Box 1)
  - Sources
    - General (Box 1)
    - Compendium Theologice Veritatis (Box 1)
  - General
    - Notes for the Manuscript Tradition of the Two Main Sources, Pope Innocent III's De Miseria Humane Conditionis and St. Bernard's Meditationes (Box 1)
    - St. Bernard's Meditationes: General and Notes (Box 1)
  - General
    - Edition of French Version of Robert Grosseteste's De Penis Purgatorii (Box 1)
  - Popularity and Audience (Box 1)
  - General
    - "Stimulus Consciencie Minor": General (Box 1)
    - "Stimulus Consciencie Minor": Manuscripts and Manuscript Descriptions (Box 1)
  - Brussels, Bibliotheque Royale, IV 998 (selections: ff. 8v-10, 48v-50)
    - Hatfield House, Deeds 59/1 (fragmentary) (Box 1)
    - London, British Library, Additional 22283 ("Simeon") (Box 1)
    - London, Lambeth Palace, 260 (selections: ff. 136v, 138-39v) (Box 1)
    - Oxford, Bodleian Library, Bodley 159 (Latin translation) (Box 1)
    - Philadelphia, University of Pennsylvania Library, English 1 (Box 1)
    - Philadelphia, University of Pennsylvania Library, English 8 (Box 1)
- Related Materials
  The series Related Materials includes files on Middle English dialects, which have played a large part in analyses of the manuscripts of the Prick of Conscience, by McIntosh and others; files on Middle English word geography, which Lewis was studying particularly in connection with the "Stimulus Consciencie Minor" and on which he had written a couple of papers; and photocopies of three manuscripts and one thesis that bear some relationship to either versions of the Prick of Conscience or the possible sources of the "Stimulus Consciencie Minor."
  - Articles (Box 2)
    - Notes (Box 2)
  - Articles and Notes
    - Papers by Lewis 1992, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Photocopies of Miscellaneous Manuscripts
    - London, British Library, Additional 37049 (Box 2)
      (selected folios; not those containing extracts from the Prick of Conscience)
    - London, British Library, Harley 275 (ff. 146v-47; a variant of Index of Middle English Verse 340) (Box 2)
    - London, British Library, Sloane 2275 (ff. 184-91; Speculum Ecclesie of St. Edmund of Abingdon) (Box 2)
  - Notes on Cards and Slips (Box 3)
  - Sources of the Prick of Conscience (Box 3)
    (4" x 6" cards)
    (alphabetically arranged by author or work)
- Microfilms of Manuscripts
  The series Microfilms of Manuscripts contains microfilm of the Prick of Conscience and related manuscripts and two related texts, chiefly in alphabetical order by the city and library in which the original manuscripts are housed, beginning with Brussels, Belgium, and ending with San Marino, California.
  - Miscellaneous Manuscripts (Small Microfilm Containers)
    - Brussels, Bibliotheque Royale Albert I, IV 998 (Box 3)
      (in red container)
    - Cambridge, Magdalene College (Box 3)
      (3 manuscripts: F.4.14, F.4.18, Pepys 1584)
      (in larger silver container)
    - Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Library, English 515 (Box 3)
      (in yellow container with orange top
    - Oxford, Bodleian Library, Bodley 99 (Box 3)
      (in black container)
    - Oxford, Merton College 69 (Box 3)
      (in smaller silver container)
    - Arnold Hahn Quellenuntersuchungen zu Richard Rolles englischen Schriften (Dissertation, Halle a/S., 1900) (Box 3)
      (in yellow container)
  - Miscellaneous Manuscripts (Large Microfilm Reels)
    - Cambridge, University Library, Box Ia (Box 3)
      (3 manuscripts, 1st filming: Dd.11.89, Dd.12.69, Ee.4.35.2; Cambridge, University Library)
    - Cambridge, University Library, Box Ib: (Box 3)
      (9 manuscripts, 1st filming: Ll.2.17, Dd.4.50, Dd.5.55, Ff.5.40, Ff.2.38, Additional 6693 Pembroke College 272, Pembroke College 273, unpublished descriptions of selected manuscripts by H.L. Pink)
    - Cambridge, University Library, Box IIa (Box 4)
      (3 manuscripts, 2nd filming: see Box Ia for contents)
    - Cambridge, University Library, Box IIb (Box 4)
      (9 manuscripts, 2nd filming: see Box Ib for contents)
    - Charlottesville, VA, University of Virginia Library, Hench 10 (Box 4)
    - Dublin, Trinity College (Box 4)
      (5 manuscripts: 69, 155, 156, 157, 158)
    - London, British Library
      - Box 1 (Box 4)
        (8 manuscripts: Arundel 140, Harley 106, Harley 3637 Royal 7 D.xxi, Royal 7 B.xvii, Additional 33957 Sloane 1044 Additional 11304)
      - Box 2 (Box 4)
        (4 manuscripts: Arundel 288, Cotton Galba E.IX, Harley 2394 Harley 4196)
      - Box 3 (Box 4)
        (3 manuscripts: Cotton Appendix VII, Egerton 657, Egerton 3245)
      - (Box 4)
        (4 manuscripts: Harley 1205 Harley 1731 Harley 2281 Harley 2377)
      - Box 5 (Box 4)
        (5 manuscripts: Harley 6923 Lansdowne 348, Royal 16 E.ii, Royal 17 C.xvii, Sloane 2275)
      - Box 6 (Box 4)
        (3 manuscripts: Royal 18 A.v, Additional 11305 Additional 24203)
      - Box 7 (Box 4)
        (2 manuscripts: Additional 25013 Additional 32578)
      - Box 8 (Box 4)
        (2 manuscripts: Additional 10053 Additional 33995)
      - Box 9 (Box 4)
        (2 manuscripts: Additional 36983 Additional 37049)
      - Box 10 (Box 4)
        (Additional 22283 known as the "Simeon MS")
    - Oxford, Bodleian Library
      - Box 1 (Box 4)
        (4 manuscripts: Additional A.268, Ashmole 41, Digby 14, Digby 87)
      - Box 2 (Box 4)
        (9 manuscripts: Digby 99, Douce 126, Douce 156, Douce 157, e Musaeo 76, e Musaeo 88, Laud Miscellaneous 486, Rawlinson A.389, Selden Supra 102*)
      - Box 3 (Box 4)
        (7 manuscripts: Lyell empt. 6, Rawlinson A.366 part 1, Rawlinson C.35, Rawlinson C.285, Rawlinson C.319, Rawlinson C.891, Rawlinson poetry 138)
      - (Box 4)
        (5 manuscripts: Rawlinson poetry 139, Rawlinson poetry 175, Trinity College 16A, Trinity College 16B, University College 142)
      - Box 5 (Box 4)
        (English poetry a. 1, known as the "Vernon MS")
      - Box 6 (Box 4)
        (4 manuscripts: Rawlinson D.913, Ashmole 52, Laud Miscellaneous 601, Bodley 423)
      - Box 7 (Box 4)
        (4 manuscripts: Junius 56, Ashmole 60, Ashmole 61, Douce 141)
      - Box 8 (Box 4)
        (2 manuscripts: e Musaeo 198, Rawlinson A.366 part 2)
    - Princeton, University Library, Garrett 138 (Box 4)
    - Princeton, University Library, Taylor MS of the Prick of Conscience (Box 4)
    - San Marino, CA, Huntington Library (Box 4)
      (4 manuscripts: HM 128, HM 125, HM 139, HM 130)
    - English and French translations of St. Bernard's Meditationes (Box 4)
      (5 manuscripts: London, British Library, Royal 16 E.xii and Royal 17 C.xvii; Oxford, Bodleian Library, Ashmole 751, Rawlinson C.894, and Rawlinson D.1502)
    - A.I. Doyle, "A Survey of the Origins and Circulation of Theological Writings in English in the 14th, 15th, and Early 16th Centuries with Special Consideration of the Part of the Clergy Therein," 2 vols. (Box 4)
      (unpublished Ph.D. thesis, Cambridge University, 1953)
- Miscellaneous Professional Files
  The series Miscellaneous Professional Files contain Lewis's selection of such files from his personal archives organized by subject in nine subdivisions, divided into files stored in standard archival folders. The files are: Celebration of Completion of the Middle English Dictionary, Middle English Dictionary Miscellaneous, Publications (Articles, Notes, etc.), Books and Reviews, Unpublished Papers on Medieval Topics, Influential Scholars, Grants and Fellowships, Awards, and Appointment and Retirement.
  The Celebration of Completion of the Middle English Dictionary file chronicles the events, activities, and publications celebrating the completion of the Middle English Dictionary (MED) in the late spring of 2001, after 71 years in progress at the University of Michigan. The series contains five files. The first consists of materials leading to, from, or growing out of the biennial meeting of the Dictionary Society of North America (DSNA) held in Ann Arbor from May 6-9, 2001. In the left-hand pocket of the file are the official schedule and a poster for the DSNA meeting; the invitation to and the menu for the celebratory dinner on May 9th; and a copy of remarks by Jay Robinson introducing Lewis before his lecture during the afternoon of the 9th. In the right-hand pocket are announcements of the completion of the MED, of a celebratory lecture series at the University of Michigan in the spring of 2001, and of four celebratory sessions at the annual medieval conference at Western Michigan University just before the DSNA meeting; catalogues of two exhibits held during the dates of the DSNA meeting; and two printed summaries of the DSNA meeting.
  The second file contains articles about the completion of the MED written between April 2001 and April 2002 arranged in chronological order. The third file contains congratulatory letters and cards to Lewis (chiefly personal) from 2001 and 2002 arranged in nearly chronological order. The fourth file contains photographs taken during some official events of the celebrations: specifically, (1) the reception at Hatcher Library during the evening of May 7th; (2) the DSNA outing to Greenfield Village during the afternoon of the 8th; (3) Lewis's lecture during the afternoon of the 9th; and (4) the celebratory dinner during the evening of the 9th. The fifth file contains the special issue on the MED of the journal Dictionaries published in 2002, which contains some of the papers presented at the DSNA meeting (and others), along with tributes and congratulations from editors of historical dictionaries around the world collected by John Simpson.
  Middle English Dictionary Miscellaneous contains four files. The first consists of articles on the MED written between 1982 and 1995 and from 2005 (for articles about the completion of the MED see the previous series). The second file contains three groups of MED"memory" items: (1) announcements and notes of congratulations on Lewis's appointment as editor of the MED, clipped together; (2) memorabilia from his time as editor and before (poems, announcements, cards, cartoons, etc.); and (3) "Excerpts from the Muddled English Dictionary," a humorous booklet produced for Alfred S. Sussman when he retired as Vice President for Research in 1985 (suggested by the MED, one of the units reporting to him). The third file contains three groups of photographs, each arranged chronologically: (1) staff and events at the MED offices, 555 South Forest, Ann Arbor (mid-1980's-2001); (2) MED staff and events off-site (1982-2001); (3) visiting Japanese scholars (1992-2002): Akio Oizumi, Hiroyuki Matsumoto, Tadao Kubouchi (not pictured), Matsuji Tajima (not pictured). The fourth file contains a compact disc of "Alphabet Odyssey," a program on the MED produced by Cindy Bisaillon on the Canadian Broadcasting Co.'s radio program "Ideas" on October 4, 2004; this disc was based in part on her interviews in Ann Arbor with MED editors and staff in 2001 and 2002.
  Publications contains two files of articles written by Lewis arranged in chronological order, 1961-1989 and 1990-2012.
  Books and Reviews contains files on three books written by Lewis himself or with others (for other books see list in first file). The first item, Lotario dei Segni (Pope Innocent III) De Miseria Condicionis Humane (Athens: University of Georgia Press, 1978; London: Scolar Press, 1980), is an edition of the most popular and influential work (written in Latin in 1194-95) on the subject of contemptus mundi ("contempt of the world"), appearing in over 670 medieval manuscripts; the 14th-century English poet Geoffrey Chaucer was heavily indebted to the work and may even have made a prose translation of it (now lost). The file on the De Miseria contains: (1) a few miscellaneous items on the edition; (2) printed reviews; and (3) Lewis's correspondence with the Hill Museum and Manuscript Library in Collegeville, MN, about depositing his microfilms and photographic reproductions of nearly 450 manuscripts of the work and related texts there.
  The second file Index of Printed Middle English Prose, with N.F. Blake and A.S.G. Edwards (New York and London: Garland Publishing Inc., 1985), is divided into: (1) correspondence 1977-91, arranged from earliest to latest, between Lewis and the other editors primarily (Blake and Edwards), as well as other scholars, about the preparation and contents of the Index; (2) reviews of the Index between 1986 and 1989, clipped together; and (3) notes (followed by articles) for a possible revised edition or supplement.